Part 2. You will hear a woman giving advice on a podcast about how to become a make-up artist
in the film industry. First, you have some time to look at questions 11 to 16.
Now, listen carefully and answer questions 11 to 16.
Hello and welcome to the Filmmaking Podcast. In this week's episode, Claire Lamar talks
to us about how to become a make-up artist. Claire has been working as a make-up artist
in the film industry for over 20 years and has lots of useful advice about how to get
started.
Thanks, Ian. Well, before you can become a make-up artist on films, you have to spend
about two years working as a make-up trainee. A good place to get your first job would be
on a low-budget short film. Of course, this means that you'll be working for free, but
it's often worth it for the experience. Make sure your transport costs are covered, and
remember, there's very unlikely to be any catering provided, so bring plenty of food.
If you're lucky, you might start out on a big-budget film, where you'll get the most
useful experience. On productions like this, make-up and hair styling are separate departments,
so you won't need to bring your curling tongs. But you're likely to get the opportunity
to work with a range of age groups, as well as different ethnicities. Doing make-up for
special effects is highly specialized, so don't expect to be offered any practical
experience in that.
One problem with working in the make-up department is that it's a high-pressure environment.
There are very few times when you'll be bored or have nothing to do. It can be stressful,
but you'll see that the top make-up artists are very professional, even when they're
having to work with directors who are impatient or unhappy with the make-up artist's work.
Follow your supervisor's lead, and try to remain calm at all times.
I have worked with many very famous actors over the years. At first, I found it overwhelming
and could hardly speak. I was so in awe. That's preferable, by the way, to becoming
too excited and asking for selfies. Now, meeting the talent is just a normal part of the job,
and to be honest, most actors don't look that special without all the make-up.
Every make-up trainee will need a make-up kit, which they'll be expected to have with
them at all times. Just the essentials will do for the kinds of tasks you'll be given.
It won't be anything complicated. It's worth looking at what the other make-up artists
have in their kits, but whatever you do, don't borrow anything without asking first.
It's very important to build your portfolio. You should take photos of all the work you
do, and ideally show the different stages of make-up application if you can. But remember,
you'll need to get approval from the make-up designer in charge of the department. As you'll
be sending your portfolio digitally, you won't need to get photos printed.
Before you hear the rest of the podcast, you have some time to look at questions 17-20.
So, what does a make-up trainee actually do? You need to think about whether you're
the right kind of person to do the job, and whether you'd enjoy it. So, to give you
some idea, here are some of the things you might be required to do. You may be asked
to help prep an actor ready for make-up. Some actors will arrive having already cleansed
and moisturized their skin. But sometimes, you'll need to step in and get this done
without wasting any time. Otherwise, the make-up artist will get behind schedule.
role in continuity. It will be your responsibility to take photos, log them digitally, and print
out a hard copy to put in each actor's file. This information needs to be kept in good
order as a reshoot can mean replicating make-up months later. General duties mean doing anything
from getting the teas and coffees to putting on a wash. Having a positive attitude and
being willing to do whatever is asked of you will help you get your next film job.
You won't be asked to apply make-up to any of the principal cast, only the extras. If there
are dozens of extras involved, you'll need to keep up a swift pace and not spend too
long on each person. It takes quite a lot of confidence to be able to do this well.
Okay, now about terms and conditions.
That is the end of part two. You now have 30 seconds to check your answers to part two.